<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Codecoupled]]></title>
  <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-08T11:19:16+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kim Persson and Lennart Fridén]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day of Confusion]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/04/day-of-confusion/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T14:27:28+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/04/day-of-confusion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Time to go to the veterinarian</h3>

<p>Today it was finally time for the visit to the veterinarian. Me and Nemah are frequent visitors due to the off and on pain in her hooves. By now I am quite used to it, but I would really like an explanation to the problems, be it good or bad, just anything. We went to a new clinic to get a second opinion on the hooves and also to check up on a lameness Nemah&rsquo;s physiotherapeut found a couple of weeks ago.</p>

<h3>Preparations</h3>

<p>Going to the vet with a horse is quite an ordeal. There are a lot of things that has to work. One thing is having a horse trailer, another is to have a car. Being as nervous as I am it&rsquo;s not really good to drive, so I also need a driver and of course you need someone to help you with the horse, if she should have a bad day.</p>

<p>With all these things in place there are some other things that are also nice to have. A clean horse, with clean hooves so the vet can stay clean.</p>

<h3>Early morning</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2052.jpg" width="400" title="look it is spring" >
So, this morning I went up way too early and arrived in the stable almost an hour before Nemah&rsquo;s private driver (my father) was due to arrive. Once he arrived we were almost ready and with a little help from Nemah&rsquo;s groom (my mother) we where soon ready to go.</p>

<p>Getting Nemah into the trailer has been a real hazzle before but today I could send her in to my mother that catched her in the front of the trailer. Amazing how easy it can be!</p>

<h3>The examination</h3>

<h4>Running</h4>

<p>Since horses generally don&rsquo;t speak you can&rsquo;t ask them where the pain is located, you have to use other means of getting the information. With horses that means a lot of running, both for her and for me. But first the vet tries to find warmth or swellings by touching all over the horse, sometimes there is a reaction. Nemah did not react.</p>

<p>So off we went to the indoor menage to lunge<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Nemah. This way we can see if she is moving normally or if there are any lameness. There were, of course. You could see something in both front legs, more on the right one, but also the right hind leg showed small signs of pain.</p>

<p>We then tried the running in a circle on a harder surface and got an even clearer result. There was definitly something wrong.</p>

<p>So, the last part of the moving examination, running back and forth on a straight line, after the vet has bent one leg joint at a time. This means several rounds, since there are at least three joints in every leg. This however did not show anything else than before, a clear sign that the problem most likely eminated from the hooves.</p>

<h4>Local Anesthesia</h4>

<p>To be more certain where the pain eminated from we decided to try and remove the pain in the different areas. We started with the right hoof, a not so fun quest as Nemah hates injections. We had to be four people to get the syringe in her leg and she still fought us all the way. After some fifteen minutes we did the running all over again, but since we already knew how the joints looke we didn&rsquo;t bend them. Now we saw that both the left hoof and the right hind leg were worse.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2053.jpg" width="400" title="Nemah, waiting for pain to let go" ></p>

<p>We then wanted to try to put anesthesia in the hind hoof as well, but by now Nemah was really tired of us and kicked when she felt the syringe. It flew 2 meters and we concluded that trying to anesthesise that hoof would be a suicide mission, so let&rsquo;s not. Instead we tried the hock<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, with a slightly better result, but not without a bit of a fight.</p>

<p>After another fifteen minutes it was time for yet another go at the running and now she started to look really good, at least where she couldn&rsquo;t feel anything.</p>

<h4>X-ray</h4>

<p>Since there was obviusly something bothering her we wanted to know more and decided to take some x-rays on the legs and hooves. To do that Nemah needs to be druged and to do that, you again have to put a needle in our poor princess. This can sometimes turn into a minor blood bath.</p>

<p><img class="middle" src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2054.jpg" width="400" title="Blood everywhere" ></p>

<p>And by the way, by some x-rays I mean like a billion (thank heavens I got salary my last week and have a good insurance for Nemah!). We x-rayed both front hooves (from all directions and including the navicular<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, the hoof and all other bones in the hoof) and the back right hoof (only from the side). Then the hock on the right hind leg (from the front, back, in and outside).</p>

<p>To make the hoof x-rays more clear they put play dough in Nemah&rsquo;s hooves.</p>

<p><img src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2055.jpg" width="400" title="Play dough to make pretty x-rays" ></p>

<p>When we looked at the images the hook looked a little bit weird so they hade to retake that one and then also did the other one for reference.</p>

<h3>Findings</h3>

<p>In the hooves &ndash; the big problem area, there was nothing. Or at least nothing that should be causing the pain Nemah experience. There was some sidebones<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, and of course the thin soles, but nothing else. In the hocks we found a shadow that looked a bit odd, since it was in both hocks it is probably spavin<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, but as long as the horse gets exercised it shouldn&rsquo;t be a problem. The rest of the joints that happened to show up on the x-ray images where all really good looking, smooth and round. So, we didn&rsquo;t really find any cause to Nemah&rsquo;s problem and the only thing we can do is keep on trying to keep her pain free.</p>

<h3>The recommendation</h3>

<p>Nemah needs to be exercised so the hocks dont get stiff. The exercise should take place on soft surfaces. The hooves will be shoed the way they are now so she doesn&rsquo;t loose her shoes but also so the seedy toe can heal. The seedy toe also needs to be a bit more cut out and she is getting anti-inflammatory medicine to stop the inflammatory process in all hooves.</p>

<p>For me, who hoped for a clear reason to her problems, be it good or not, this was not at all what I hoped for. Now I still have a horse that <em>should be ok</em> as long as we make sure not to trigger anything. I have a horse that maybe can handle ordinary ridning or she may not&hellip; What remains is a confused horse owner, that doesn&rsquo;t really know what to do.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longeing">Longeing</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hock_(anatomy">Hock</a>)<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navicular_syndrome">Navicular</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bone_spavin">Spavin</a><a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sidebone">Sidebone</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Walking the Walk]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/03/walking-the-walk/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T22:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/03/walking-the-walk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Week 1</h2>

<h3>Monday morning, weekly planning meeting</h3>

<p><em>- How about mob programming<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> this on Wednesday?</em></p>

<p>Over the past few weeks, the team had worked in pairs on separate parts of a new system. However, the previous week had been interrupted by illness and meetings so I felt we had to pool our collective knowledge in order to grasp where we were and where we were heading. Thus, we set aside a day intent on bringing everyone up to speed.</p>

<p>The days before the scheduled mob programming session seemed to me ever so slow. I didn&rsquo;t feel exceptionally motivated in general and despite my best intentions I never took the initative to pair program. Pleasently enough I was ambushed by our most recent addition to the team with a &ldquo;I&rsquo;m going to pair with you now&rdquo;. It&rsquo;s really not more difficult than that.</p>

<h3>Wednesday, first day of mob programming</h3>

<p>We got going at around 10 o&#8217;clock as that&rsquo;s when the entire team can be expected to be in the office. The morning was used to go through the various parts we already had, taking note of missing or poorly understood pieces and tasks. Most importantly, we settled on a bare minimum of things that had to be done before we could reach something shippable. Just before lunch we got started on the actual mob programming. A conference room, a beamer, a computer, and someone making sure that the driver was swapped every fifteen minutes. It doesn&rsquo;t take more than that to start.</p>

<p>Shortly after lunch, one of us had to leave early, and as would be shown over and over again during our mob programming sessions, here&rsquo;s when one of mob programming&rsquo;s greatest strengths comes into play. Had the abscent team member being working alone on a task, the work would simply stop. Mob programming mitigates this problem as the rest of the mob simply continues working. It&rsquo;s similar to what would happen in a pair programming session, except that there&rsquo;s practially no degradation in performace. Phrased differently, if pair programming is RAID 1, mob programming is RAID 5 with spare disks<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p><em>- So how did this feel?</em></p>

<p>At the end of the day we had made some progress, primarily in understanding where we were and where we were going. We held a short restrospective to gauge what the team though of the day. Unanimously we agreed to continue the next day.</p>

<h3>Thursday, second day of mob programming</h3>

<p>The second day went smoother than the first day. We continued to be a team member short, but that didn&rsquo;t stop us. Just like the day before, we held a brief retrospective. Just like the day before, we agreed to continue the next day. Though no-one questioned mob programming being effective given our set goals, the question regarding efficency was raised. I certainly don&rsquo;t have a definitive answer, but to me there are so many more aspects to factor in than those that can be directly measured and quantified.</p>

<p>For example, of all my experiences during our mob programming experiment, this day held the most surprising one of them all. Walking home from the commuter train it struck me that I generally liked my team better. Not that I didn&rsquo;t like each and everyone before, I just liked them <em>more</em> after <em>continously</em> working together.</p>

<h3>Friday, third day of mob programming</h3>

<p>At this point, we had really gotten into rythm of mob programming. We concluded the week with a slightly longer retrospective and hesitantly I spoke my heart&rsquo;s desire.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://i948.photobucket.com/albums/ad326/DevLCSC/Codecoupled/IMG_1812_zpsfd729abf.jpg" width="390" title="At the end of the first week" ></p>

<p><em>- Well, since there&rsquo;s work still left to be done and the office will be mostly vacant next week, thus freeing up the conference room, how about extending this experiment to all of next week?</em></p>

<p>The resounding &ldquo;yes&rdquo; and &ldquo;let&rsquo;s finish what we&rsquo;ve started&rdquo; I got in response almost made me wish that the weekend would pass swiftly. I took heart in that the following week would be one of mob programming.</p>

<p>Because the team chose to.</p>

<h2>Week 2</h2>

<h3>Monday, fourth day of mob programming</h3>

<p><em>- We don&rsquo;t need to open a pull request.</em></p>

<p>Over the weekend a team member fell ill, but we regained another so on the whole the mob remained four strong. One of the first things pointed out to us by the returning team member was that we really didn&rsquo;t have to use a feature branch as there was no branching going on, especially as the new app was yet to be deployed to production.</p>

<p>The weekly planning meeting had us pause the ongoing work in favour of a number of smaller, but higher priority, tasks. Admittedly, for two of these, the mob turned out to be overkill and in hindsight we would probably have been better served by splitting off one or two team members to tackle the smaller tasks while keeping the mob focused on the main task. Nevertheless, it was a valuable learning experience to handle even these simple tasks as a mob.</p>

<p>In the afternoon, following a failed ice cream break turned into a coffee break, an iOS developer sat in out of curiosity just as we touched upon something that required his input. While it&rsquo;s not a particular property of mob programming itself, being able to pick a stake holders&#8217; brain directly while working is not be underestimated.</p>

<h3>Tuesday, fifth day of mob programming</h3>

<p>Tuesday saw us returning to the main task in earnest. The day started slowly with various technical hickups during setup, wasting time. In hindsight, I cannot stress the value of having a good setup when mob programming, but at the time we deemed what we had to be good enough for the experiment.</p>

<p>During the daily retrospective the concern that compared to when pair programming, it took longer time to agree on what to focus on and make decisions. The counter point was made that consensus is worth taking time and that any decision thusly made would be stronger.</p>

<p>In the end we settled on the person in front of the keyboard being the tie breaker.</p>

<h3>Wednesday, sixth day of mob programming</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i948.photobucket.com/albums/ad326/DevLCSC/Codecoupled/IMG_1825_zps397aea7c.jpg" width="288" title="Rotations" ></p>

<p>Despite another round of technical problems and fiddling with editor themes to make the code visible enough we made good progress and got no fewer than twenty rotations done. The format of taking timed turns at the keyboard, rotating through the entire mob, rather than the usual ping-pong pair programming style we&rsquo;re accustomed to did not impress everyone.</p>

<p><em>- I feel I get to code to little, it&rsquo;s hard to stay focused on the main task, and frankly, that&rsquo;s a bit boring.</em></p>

<p><em>- I was like that last week, but I&rsquo;ve gotten better. I can&rsquo;t say that will be the case for you too.</em></p>

<p>The exchange<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> between two of my team mates left me both heartend and disheartend. Without the entire team getting behind mob programming, I didn&rsquo;t see it happening much beyond the current experiment.</p>

<h3>Thursday, seventh day of mob programming</h3>

<p>Even in a nearly empty office, you can&rsquo;t spirit away the entire backend team and occupy the main conference room without curious colleagues wondering what we were up to. Not only did I get to talk about what mob programming is about over lunch, but our marketing department snapped a few shots of the mob and asked a couple of questions intended for a report in our internal weekly news app<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Such distractions aside, this day turned out to be very productive and even the most sceptical of us agreed that it had been a good day.</p>

<h3>Friday, eighth day of mob programming</h3>

<p>Our last day of mob programming was also the first day we had the entire team present. The morning saw us testing and polishing what we had built. Even after a lengthy discussion and a longer break around lunch than usual we managed to complete an unplanned, but high priority task. As one of us had to leave early, we decided to postpone the overall mob programming retrospective until the week after. Of course, it turned out that another team member is on vacation then.</p>

<p>Bonus lesson learned: don&rsquo;t postpone retrospectives, rather have more of them if and as needed.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Both Kim and I have previously tinkered and toyed with the concept of mob programming in various contexts<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, but I feel that this was the first time I got to mob program <em>for real</em>. Working as a mob for a few hours or a day at most simply doesn&rsquo;t capture the many nuances and experiences that the past week and a half has brought me.</p>

<p>After recapitulating the events of our mob programming experiment, what was the outcome? Will we continue mob programming? As I write these words, I&rsquo;ve yet to find out for myself.</p>

<p>Personally, I wish I could say it was successful in convincing the team and beyond to keep mob programming more or less all the time. However, I have my doubts that will be the case. I do hope we will revisit the concept, adapt it in whatever manner needed to make sure we get the most out of it without having qualms over perceived efficiency and attention span get in the way.</p>

<p>Nevertheless I consider the experiment to be successful beyond my wildest expectations. It was successful in the sense that we got the job done. It was successful in the sense that we spread knowledge and shared insights about all the moving parts. It was successful in engaging and motivating the entire team to work closer together.</p>

<p>Above all, it was successful in the sense that we had fun together. At the end of the day, I can&rsquo;t think of higher praise to be given by a team than this:</p>

<p><em>- This was fun, let&rsquo;s do it again!</em></p>

<p><img src="http://i948.photobucket.com/albums/ad326/DevLCSC/Codecoupled/IMG_1827_zps2ea09470.jpg?t=1393870040" title="The team with me behind the camera" ></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="http://mobprogramming.org/mob-programming-basics/">An introduction to mobprogramming.org</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RAID">Wikipedia on RAID</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Somewhat paraphrased and abbreviated, but accurate enough.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>You don&rsquo;t expect a <a href="http://www.magplus.com">company building a publishing platform</a> to use email for its internal newsletter, do you?<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See <a href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/02/01/mob-refactoring/">Mob Refactoring</a> for a record of Kim&rsquo;s experience at her work.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mob Refactoring]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/02/01/mob-refactoring/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-01T20:00:37+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/02/01/mob-refactoring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today at work we tried mob refactoring, which is just like mob programming, but instead of creating new code you refactor existing code. Our goal was mostly to spread knowledge within the group, to even out the knowledge a bit and also practise refactoring. We are lucky enough to have a projector in our room so we fired it up and started.</p>

<p>The thing we wanted to refactor was one of our most central classes, which has almost 300 lines of code. We decided that the most experienced refactorer would not be writing any code, he would only be a navigator, the rest of us would both drive and navigate and we changed driver every 10 minutes. We did this for about an hour.</p>

<h3>Results (some of them just from my point of view)</h3>

<p>All the drivers felt really stupid behind the keyboard, we stumbled on the keys and at times at least I felt like I had no idea what to do, or where to do it. However I really liked being just a stupid input device and getting to concentrate on just writing what I was told to.</p>

<p>The decision to let the less experienced drive resulted in the code being written slower. That in turn gave us all a possibility to read and contemplate the code and what to do next. I have found that when a more experienced person drives there is a risk they already know exactly what to do and have done it before the lesser experienced has had the time to really grasp the problem.</p>

<p>Another good thing that came out of the mob refactoring session was the friendly, constructive discussion. We shared tips and tricks about the editor, about the code and how to make it better. Some of these tips are things someone could do in a short period of time as a preparation for a future refactoring.</p>

<p>At the retro we held afterward, everyone really liked the mob refactoring and we all wanted to do it again. We decided to do it every Wednesday morning for an hour.</p>

<p>The only thing I found not to be as good was that we had two screens. The big one everyone was looking at, pointing at and commenting, and then the smaller one on the laptop in front of the driver. When being the driver, I sometimes got a bit confused not knowing what the others where talking about in the code since my eyes naturally was drawn to the smaller screen that was closer to me and by doing that I missed where the others where pointing .</p>

<p>All in all it was a great experience and I would love to do more of it.</p>

<p>If you want to read more: <br/>
<a href="http://blog.codeclimate.com/blog/2014/01/30/mob-refactoring/">mob refactoring</a><br/>
<a href="http://mobprogramming.org/">mob programming</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Horses Give Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/01/01/what-horses-give-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T22:45:25+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/01/01/what-horses-give-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People often ask what I find so fantastic with horses. So I figured I could spend my first blog post letting you know some of the things that make me come back to horses again and again. This is just some of the things that happened on a rather ordinary day in the stable, but no day is the same.</p>

<h4>I get to work with my body</h4>

<p>Due to the last days of heavy rain, the litter in Nemah&rsquo;s box had turned really wet and it could not be saved. So I removed eight full wheelbarrows of wet litter mixed with shit and pee, and put in about 100 kg of new, fresh, clean litter. A perfect workout!</p>

<h4>I get practice in the art of saying no</h4>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1983.jpg" width="200" title="Timon, the cuddle cat" >
Being a cat lover I take every opportunity to cuddle with the stable cat, Timon. Timon is a real cuddle cat and once you start to cuddle he really, really, really won&rsquo;t let you go. Eventually I had to tell him to stop walk all over me, drool and purr, even though he really didn&rsquo;t want to stop.</p>

<h4>I get my feet back on the ground</h4>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1986.jpg" width="250" title="Many feathers, but no hen" >
On occasion the environment around the stable can give you quite a chock. This day I found this very local pile of snow. When I took a closer look I realised it wasn&rsquo;t snow, it was the remains of a poor hen that stayed out to late at night and met a fox. All that was left of her where these feathers. It reminds me of how short life can be and that I really should make the most of the short time I have on this earth.</p>

<h4>I practice patience</h4>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1987.jpg" width="250" title="Injured hoof" >
Nemah has had an injured hoof for the last 2.5 years and every day I have been washing it and making sure it&rsquo;s not muddy. For those of you that don&rsquo;t spend time around horses, they are true masters of making mud and then stepping in it. There have been times when I haven&rsquo;t been able to do anything but wash the hoof, so I have learnt that patience really is a virtue.</p>

<h4>I learn to see beauty in the smallest things</h4>

<p>Even a couple of fence poles just lying on the ground can be really beautiful in the right light.<br/>
<img src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1985.jpg" width="250" title="fence poles in the sun" ></p>

<h4>I get to enjoy the here and now</h4>

<p>A ride with Nemah is always a pleasure. She enjoys a stroll in the woods just as much as a fast canter on the sand roads. The faster we go, the more her ears are pointing forward, a telltale sign that she is enjoing herself. But Nemah is also a very sensitive horse, with big ears and eyes. She can see and hear things I don&rsquo;t, thus making me stay focused on what we do and where we are. The perfect way to stay in the moment and let all troubles go.<br/>
<img src="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1989.jpg" title="Ride in the sun" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
