<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Nemah | Codecoupled]]></title>
  <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/categories/nemah/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-28T21:36:31+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kim Persson and Lennart Fridén]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Saving Princess Nemah]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/25/saving-princess-nemah/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T14:34:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/25/saving-princess-nemah</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2074.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2074.jpg</a>" width="400" title="Ready to go, a wee bit sceptic" ></p>

<p>Since Nemah&rsquo;s last visit to the veterinarian three weeks ago we have given Nemah anti-inflammatory medication to ease her pain. Her hooves are better, but the left hoof has been acting up, being warm and the leg has been swollen. Since this is a recurring problem I decided to let one of Swedens best farriers take a look and see if he might be able to help her. He comes to Stockholm once every 2 weeks and work on the clinic we went to last time. Said and done, we went to meet him, and also let the veterinarian take a second look at Nemah.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2075.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2075.jpg</a>" width="400" title="Showing your credentials" ></p>

<p>After some running on soft and hard surfaces the vet. agreed with me that the right hoof was better, but the left one was worse. Let&rsquo;s get the farrier to look at it! And then we waited, which is something you can expect when meeting a farrier, it takes a lot of time to get hooves perfect and horses are not always as cooperative as you would want them to be.</p>

<p>I brought with me my ordinary farrier to be sure she also understood the problem and maybe even could help with the solution, if we found one. The new farrier took of the shoes and examined the hoves and angles thoroughly. He opened up the seedy toe even more, there is no idea trying to save the parts of the hoof wall that isn&rsquo;t healthy, so the hole is now even bigger. You can actually see how far up it was opened before if you take a good look.
<img class="left <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2077.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2077.jpg</a>" width="400" title="Seedy toe cleaned out" ></p>

<p>When the seedy toe was all cleaned out he pressed the soles of Nemahs hooves and they turned up up to be really soft and flexing. They should be hard och not flexible at all. When they flex it means that the sole is really thin and very sensitive. With a thin sole it is like walking barefoot, every little stone hurts and a bigger stone can even result in a bleeding in the hoof and that is really painful!</p>

<p>Some thinking and discussion later he decided to put Equi-Pak in the hooves. I have never seen that before so it was really interesting. First he cut out a net in the same size as the shoe and then put the net and shoe on the hoof (the first time he forgot to put the net in between the hoof and shoe and had to redo that hoof. After that you place the hoof on a sticky foam rubber plate.
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2080.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2080.jpg</a>" width="300" title="Letting the Equo-Pak stiffen" ></p>

<p>You then put in the Equi-Pak, a kind of liquid urethane. The farrier pressed it in between the hoof and the net and let it stiffen. Once it has stiffen it gives the hoof extra protection that works a bit like the hoof itself would.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2079.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2079.jpg</a>" width="300" title="Equi Pak going in" ></p>

<p>Once the Equi-Pak had stiffen the farrier put some polish on the hooves and Nemah&rsquo;s manicure was done for this day.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2082.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2082.jpg</a>" width="400" title="All done, with nail polish on top" >
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2083.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2083.jpg</a>" width="300" title="You can see the net" ></p>

<p>With these new shoes Nemah is hopefully going to feel less pain from her hooves and we can start riding more properly again, which we have to to keep her hocks happy..</p>

<p>As usual, this day would not have been possible without Nemahs private driver, her private groom and of course her wonderful co-rider. I can&rsquo;t even begin to tell how happy I am to have all of them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day of Confusion]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/04/day-of-confusion/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T14:27:28+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/03/04/day-of-confusion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Time to go to the veterinarian</h3>

<p>Today it was finally time for the visit to the veterinarian. Me and Nemah are frequent visitors due to the off and on pain in her hooves. By now I am quite used to it, but I would really like an explanation to the problems, be it good or bad, just anything. We went to a new clinic to get a second opinion on the hooves and also to check up on a lameness Nemah&rsquo;s physiotherapeut found a couple of weeks ago.</p>

<h3>Preparations</h3>

<p>Going to the vet with a horse is quite an ordeal. There are a lot of things that has to work. One thing is having a horse trailer, another is to have a car. Being as nervous as I am it&rsquo;s not really good to drive, so I also need a driver and of course you need someone to help you with the horse, if she should have a bad day.</p>

<p>With all these things in place there are some other things that are also nice to have. A clean horse, with clean hooves so the vet can stay clean.</p>

<h3>Early morning</h3>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2052.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2052.jpg</a>" width="400" title="look it is spring" >
So, this morning I went up way too early and arrived in the stable almost an hour before Nemah&rsquo;s private driver (my father) was due to arrive. Once he arrived we were almost ready and with a little help from Nemah&rsquo;s groom (my mother) we where soon ready to go.</p>

<p>Getting Nemah into the trailer has been a real hazzle before but today I could send her in to my mother that catched her in the front of the trailer. Amazing how easy it can be!</p>

<h3>The examination</h3>

<h4>Running</h4>

<p>Since horses generally don&rsquo;t speak you can&rsquo;t ask them where the pain is located, you have to use other means of getting the information. With horses that means a lot of running, both for her and for me. But first the vet tries to find warmth or swellings by touching all over the horse, sometimes there is a reaction. Nemah did not react.</p>

<p>So off we went to the indoor menage to lunge<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Nemah. This way we can see if she is moving normally or if there are any lameness. There were, of course. You could see something in both front legs, more on the right one, but also the right hind leg showed small signs of pain.</p>

<p>We then tried the running in a circle on a harder surface and got an even clearer result. There was definitly something wrong.</p>

<p>So, the last part of the moving examination, running back and forth on a straight line, after the vet has bent one leg joint at a time. This means several rounds, since there are at least three joints in every leg. This however did not show anything else than before, a clear sign that the problem most likely eminated from the hooves.</p>

<h4>Local Anesthesia</h4>

<p>To be more certain where the pain eminated from we decided to try and remove the pain in the different areas. We started with the right hoof, a not so fun quest as Nemah hates injections. We had to be four people to get the syringe in her leg and she still fought us all the way. After some fifteen minutes we did the running all over again, but since we already knew how the joints looke we didn&rsquo;t bend them. Now we saw that both the left hoof and the right hind leg were worse.</p>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2053.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2053.jpg</a>" width="400" title="Nemah, waiting for pain to let go" ></p>

<p>We then wanted to try to put anesthesia in the hind hoof as well, but by now Nemah was really tired of us and kicked when she felt the syringe. It flew 2 meters and we concluded that trying to anesthesise that hoof would be a suicide mission, so let&rsquo;s not. Instead we tried the hock<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, with a slightly better result, but not without a bit of a fight.</p>

<p>After another fifteen minutes it was time for yet another go at the running and now she started to look really good, at least where she couldn&rsquo;t feel anything.</p>

<h4>X-ray</h4>

<p>Since there was obviusly something bothering her we wanted to know more and decided to take some x-rays on the legs and hooves. To do that Nemah needs to be druged and to do that, you again have to put a needle in our poor princess. This can sometimes turn into a minor blood bath.</p>

<p><img class="middle <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2054.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2054.jpg</a>" width="400" title="Blood everywhere" ></p>

<p>And by the way, by some x-rays I mean like a billion (thank heavens I got salary my last week and have a good insurance for Nemah!). We x-rayed both front hooves (from all directions and including the navicular<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, the hoof and all other bones in the hoof) and the back right hoof (only from the side). Then the hock on the right hind leg (from the front, back, in and outside).</p>

<p>To make the hoof x-rays more clear they put play dough in Nemah&rsquo;s hooves.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2055.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_2055.jpg</a>" width="400" title="Play dough to make pretty x-rays" ></p>

<p>When we looked at the images the hook looked a little bit weird so they hade to retake that one and then also did the other one for reference.</p>

<h3>Findings</h3>

<p>In the hooves &ndash; the big problem area, there was nothing. Or at least nothing that should be causing the pain Nemah experience. There was some sidebones<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, and of course the thin soles, but nothing else. In the hocks we found a shadow that looked a bit odd, since it was in both hocks it is probably spavin<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, but as long as the horse gets exercised it shouldn&rsquo;t be a problem. The rest of the joints that happened to show up on the x-ray images where all really good looking, smooth and round. So, we didn&rsquo;t really find any cause to Nemah&rsquo;s problem and the only thing we can do is keep on trying to keep her pain free.</p>

<h3>The recommendation</h3>

<p>Nemah needs to be exercised so the hocks dont get stiff. The exercise should take place on soft surfaces. The hooves will be shoed the way they are now so she doesn&rsquo;t loose her shoes but also so the seedy toe can heal. The seedy toe also needs to be a bit more cut out and she is getting anti-inflammatory medicine to stop the inflammatory process in all hooves.</p>

<p>For me, who hoped for a clear reason to her problems, be it good or not, this was not at all what I hoped for. Now I still have a horse that <em>should be ok</em> as long as we make sure not to trigger anything. I have a horse that maybe can handle ordinary ridning or she may not&hellip; What remains is a confused horse owner, that doesn&rsquo;t really know what to do.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longeing">Longeing</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hock_(anatomy">Hock</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navicular_syndrome">Navicular</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bone_spavin">Spavin</a><a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sidebone">Sidebone</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Horses Give Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/01/01/what-horses-give-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T22:45:25+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/01/01/what-horses-give-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People often ask what I find so fantastic with horses. So I figured I could spend my first blog post letting you know some of the things that make me come back to horses again and again. This is just some of the things that happened on a rather ordinary day in the stable, but no day is the same.</p>

<h4>I get to work with my body</h4>

<p>Due to the last days of heavy rain, the litter in Nemah&rsquo;s box had turned really wet and it could not be saved. So I removed eight full wheelbarrows of wet litter mixed with shit and pee, and put in about 100 kg of new, fresh, clean litter. A perfect workout!</p>

<h4>I get practice in the art of saying no</h4>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1983.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1983.jpg</a>" width="200" title="Timon, the cuddle cat" >
Being a cat lover I take every opportunity to cuddle with the stable cat, Timon. Timon is a real cuddle cat and once you start to cuddle he really, really, really won&rsquo;t let you go. Eventually I had to tell him to stop walk all over me, drool and purr, even though he really didn&rsquo;t want to stop.</p>

<h4>I get my feet back on the ground</h4>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1986.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1986.jpg</a>" width="250" title="Many feathers, but no hen" >
On occasion the environment around the stable can give you quite a chock. This day I found this very local pile of snow. When I took a closer look I realised it wasn&rsquo;t snow, it was the remains of a poor hen that stayed out to late at night and met a fox. All that was left of her where these feathers. It reminds me of how short life can be and that I really should make the most of the short time I have on this earth.</p>

<h4>I practice patience</h4>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1987.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1987.jpg</a>" width="250" title="Injured hoof" >
Nemah has had an injured hoof for the last 2.5 years and every day I have been washing it and making sure it&rsquo;s not muddy. For those of you that don&rsquo;t spend time around horses, they are true masters of making mud and then stepping in it. There have been times when I haven&rsquo;t been able to do anything but wash the hoof, so I have learnt that patience really is a virtue.</p>

<h4>I learn to see beauty in the smallest things</h4>

<p>Even a couple of fence poles just lying on the ground can be really beautiful in the right light.<br/>
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1985.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1985.jpg</a>" width="250" title="fence poles in the sun" ></p>

<h4>I get to enjoy the here and now</h4>

<p>A ride with Nemah is always a pleasure. She enjoys a stroll in the woods just as much as a fast canter on the sand roads. The faster we go, the more her ears are pointing forward, a telltale sign that she is enjoing herself. But Nemah is also a very sensitive horse, with big ears and eyes. She can see and hear things I don&rsquo;t, thus making me stay focused on what we do and where we are. The perfect way to stay in the moment and let all troubles go.<br/>
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1989.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1989.jpg</a>" title="Ride in the sun" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
