<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Horses | Codecoupled]]></title>
  <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/categories/horses/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-03T22:37:17+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kim Persson and Lennart Fridén]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Horses Give Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/01/01/what-horses-give-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T22:45:25+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DevL.github.io/codecoupled/blog/2014/01/01/what-horses-give-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People often ask what I find so fantastic with horses. So I figured I could spend my first blog post letting you know some of the things that make me come back to horses again and again. This is just some of the things that happened on a rather ordinary day in the stable, but no day is the same.</p>

<h4>I get to work with my body</h4>

<p>Due to the last days of heavy rain, the litter in Nemah&rsquo;s box had turned really wet and it could not be saved. So I removed eight full wheelbarrows of wet litter mixed with shit and pee, and put in about 100 kg of new, fresh, clean litter. A perfect workout!</p>

<h4>I get practice in the art of saying no</h4>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1983.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1983.jpg</a>" width="200" title="Timon, the cuddle cat" >
Being a cat lover I take every opportunity to cuddle with the stable cat, Timon. Timon is a real cuddle cat and once you start to cuddle he really, really, really won&rsquo;t let you go. Eventually I had to tell him to stop walk all over me, drool and purr, even though he really didn&rsquo;t want to stop.</p>

<h4>I get my feet back on the ground</h4>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1986.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1986.jpg</a>" width="250" title="Many feathers, but no hen" >
On occasion the environment around the stable can give you quite a chock. This day I found this very local pile of snow. When I took a closer look I realised it wasn&rsquo;t snow, it was the remains of a poor hen that stayed out to late at night and met a fox. All that was left of her where these feathers. It reminds me of how short life can be and that I really should make the most of the short time I have on this earth.</p>

<h4>I practice patience</h4>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1987.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1987.jpg</a>" width="250" title="Injured hoof" >
Nemah has had an injured hoof for the last 2.5 years and every day I have been washing it and making sure it&rsquo;s not muddy. For those of you that don&rsquo;t spend time around horses, they are true masters of making mud and then stepping in it. There have been times when I haven&rsquo;t been able to do anything but wash the hoof, so I have learnt that patience really is a virtue.</p>

<h4>I learn to see beauty in the smallest things</h4>

<p>Even a couple of fence poles just lying on the ground can be really beautiful in the right light.<br/>
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1985.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1985.jpg</a>" width="250" title="fence poles in the sun" ></p>

<h4>I get to enjoy the here and now</h4>

<p>A ride with Nemah is always a pleasure. She enjoys a stroll in the woods just as much as a fast canter on the sand roads. The faster we go, the more her ears are pointing forward, a telltale sign that she is enjoing herself. But Nemah is also a very sensitive horse, with big ears and eyes. She can see and hear things I don&rsquo;t, thus making me stay focused on what we do and where we are. The perfect way to stay in the moment and let all troubles go.<br/>
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1989.jpg">http://i60.photobucket.com/albums/h13/Forgetmenotox/Codecoupled/IMG_1989.jpg</a>" title="Ride in the sun" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
